In the past, I've released plenty of
analyses on how coffee is a benefit to
our health, especially for our heart
health. However, although we can look at
large data sets and get a general idea,
we need to go through with a finer tooth
comb to catch exceptions. And that's
what the research has started to
uncover. As they began looking at how
people prepare their coffee, finding
that one method continues this trend of
improved health from coffee consumption,
while another method leads to the
reversal or even health harm. So, what
are the methods and why is there
difference in the effects on our health?
And how likely are you to rip me limb
from limb if I tell you that coffee's
now unhealthy for you?
Well, I'll answer the last one now. It's
highly unlikely because that's not going
to be the conclusion here. As for the
first question, what kind of methods?
We're talking about two broad camps. So,
one is filtered coffee and the other's
unfiltered coffee. Now, I'll get into
more specifics of each later, but that
distinction is enough to identify a
difference in the health effects. Now,
interestingly, in this initial study
that I had on screen, there were about
half a million participants, so men and
women including all age ranges from 20
to 80. And when looking at the data
split by men and women, we see a bunch
of numbers. But, I don't want this to be
a boring numbers presentation, so I'll
leave the data up for those that know
how to read it and I'll highlight a few
specifics in graph form here. Now, both
of these graphs are total mortality
risk, so dying from any cause. We have
four groups, those that consume no
coffee, the heathens, those that consume
both forms of brewing, and then the
filtered and unfiltered individually.
The yellow vertical line indicates a
neutral relationship, and if the red
lines and dots move to the left, that
means reduced risk of death from all
causes compared to those who don't
consume any coffee. So, funny enough,
these data corroborate past data
indicating that coffee overall is
probably a benefit to our health. You
can breathe again. But, you'll note that
the benefit of unfiltered coffee tends
to lag behind by a bit or be
nonexistent. Still, nothing here
indicates harm. So, why is there any
concern at all?
It comes down to this, a peculiar
phenomenon that makes age a major
factor. Same rules that apply as last
time, and I'm focusing on men here, but
similar trends are seen in women, just
not as extensively. For those under the
age of 60, there's a reduced risk of
cardiovascular death death, even with
unfiltered coffee. However, in those
over 60, the risk flips for the same
unfiltered coffee. Suddenly, risk of
death increases, not seen with filtered
coffee. So, the main point here is that
the filtered coffee has a consistent
track record of being neutral or
positive for health. Unfiltered coffee
has a much more mixed track record with
harmful relationship identified in those
over 60. Okay, interesting, but why
exactly? Well, there's a number of
reasons. The researchers of this study
that we've been leaning on mentioned
that unfiltered coffee can raise blood
cholesterol levels, and that has been
verified a few times over in these
studies. So, okay, fair enough if that
happens, and when we do adjustments,
meaning that we remove blood cholesterol
as a factor statistically, the
researchers do mention that there's a
reduced relationship with ischemic heart
disease. That now that's a type of heart
disease where the plaque builds up in
the blood vessels of the heart. But, I
remain unconvinced because while the
relationship is weakened, implying that
blood cholesterol does play a role here,
it isn't eliminated. The relationship
partly remains. That means that there's
something else going on here, too. Also,
although we know that unfiltered coffee
raises blood cholesterol, the studies
directly testing this use pretty large
amounts of coffee, so we're talking
almost a liter per day just to see an 11
mg per deciliter increase. Maybe we'd
see similar increases with less
consumed, but regardless, there is a
cholesterol effect here. It just doesn't
explain everything.
There are other possibilities like the
fact that the researchers adjust or
statistically control for a variety of
factors here, but they do not do any
specific controls for diet or diet
quality. This could be a major hole that
explains the remaining relationship. We
don't know. The bottom line, we aren't
entirely clear on the mechanisms, though
we do know some of them. Regardless,
there's some easy takeaways that we can
still get from all this research. Now,
before that, this may not be for you,
but if you want a more detailed analysis
on the amounts of coffee related to
health, more on the statistics, and
other such nerdities, then check out my
full analysis on this topic, part of the
PhysioTrek Insider subscription. Plus,
you get all these perks right here,
including a monthly podcast covering a
series of topics only for the insiders,
or you can also join me in live sessions
and the rest of the insider community.
I'm actually going to be doing one of
those live sessions this Sunday. So,
link to join us in the description box,
and I hope to see you there. All right.
So, some easy takeaways.
Well, when we're talking about
unfiltered coffee, we're talking about
coffee brewing techniques like the
French press, boiled coffee like
Norwegian boiled coffee, Turkish and
Greek coffee,
espresso. And this actually might
surprise some of you. You know those uh
single-serve pods used in certain like
companies and often in hotel rooms?
Those are also unfiltered. So, the
bottom line is this, filtered coffee
continues to have a positive health
track record. Unfiltered coffee has a
less positive track record and likely
should be avoided when possible. Now,
the occasional drink isn't going to do
much, just don't want it to be regularly
consumed. So, stick to a paper filter
coffee. It's important that it's paper
filtered as the other filters aren't
fine enough to eliminate the harmful
molecules trapped in the filter. So,
that's a few simple things to act on,
but there's actually more to coffee than
you might think. In this video right
here, I go over more on some pitfalls
that turn coffee from healthy to
unhealthy. I'll catch you over there.
Thanks for tuning in. I'll speak with
you soon again. Bye.